Haruna Adoga, PhD

Glasgow, United Kingdom.

Lecturing | HPC Systems | Distributed Edge/Cloud Computing Networks +44 7767943721, +234 8023836922 | Haruna.Umar.Adoga@gmail.com | <u>LinkedIn</u> | Google Scholar

About

Dr Haruna Adoga has over ten years of academic and industry experience in systems and network engineering, focusing on cloud and distributed edge computing systems. He has experience and training as a researcher in computing science, with research and teaching endeavours in computing systems, high-performance computing, intelligent virtual network management and cybersecurity. He is an active member of the British Computer Society (BCS), the IEEE, the Institution of Engineering and Technology (IET), the Nigeria Computer Society (NCS), and the Nigeria Society of Engineers (NSE).

Experience

Research Computing Engineer

August 2023 – Present

University of Sussex, England, UK

- Design of a private cloud HPC infrastructure for Research Computing
- Collaborating with industry and research experts in delivering tailored HPC solutions
- Providing design and technical support in troubleshooting problems with HPC clusters and Linux systems
- Carrying out upgrades and applying security patches on Linux/Unix systems for scientific computing
- Training researchers on the use of scientific computing infrastructure for high-performance computing
- Performing Linux/UNIX system administration and design, including storage and web server hosting with Nginx
- Hands-on experience with HPC management and monitoring tools: SNMP, Nagios, IPMI

Researcher & Graduate Teaching Assistant

January 2020 – January 2024

University of Glasgow, Scotland, UK

- Tutoring undergraduate students on Human-Computer Interaction and Information Management
- Tutoring level 2 students on Networks and Operating Systems Essentials 2
- Tutoring students on data science, AI, SQL and Cybersecurity
- Assisting with the marking of coursework and examination for MSc level and undergraduate courses
- Teaching practical aspects of advanced programming using Python for MSc students
- Practical and theoretical teaching of Information Technology course for MSc Web development with Python (Django framework)

University Lecturer - Computer Science

May 2012 – Present

Federal University Lafia, Nigeria

- Delivering lectures in computer programming using Python and Java
- Presenting theoretical and practical lectures on networks, distributed computing and cloud computing
- Lecturing cybersecurity and data structures to pre-undergrads
- Delivering lectures on Machine Learning and AI application on computer networks
- Supervising undergraduate and postgraduate projects
- Lecturing undergraduate and postgraduate diploma students courses in parallel computing and operating systems
- Delivering lectures on databases and parallel computing

Education

University of Glasgow

Glasgow, UK

PhD. Computing Science

Jan 2020 to May 2024

University of Hertfordshire

Hertfordshire, UK July 2014 to Jan 2016

MSc. Computing Science

University of Maiduguri

Beng. E & E Engineering

Last updated on July 13, 2024

Maiduguri, Nigeria
Page April₃2004 to Dec 2009

Skills Summary

Research and Industry Certifications: Scientific paper reviews, Cisco CCNA, CCNP, AWS Cloud Practitioner Networking and Systems: LAN, HPC, Cloud, Edge computing, WAN, VPC, NFV, InfiniBand, BGP, Switching, RedHat, Kali, Ubuntu, Routing

Development Tools/Languages: Python, Java, Bash Scripting, Git, Docker, Django AWS, Ansible, Terraform, Gen AI, SQL

Applications/Libraries: Wireshark, VMWare, Teams, Office, Powerpoint, KVM, Jira, NetworkX, Numpy, Matplotlib, Scapy, Overleaf

IT Certifications and Professional Memberships

Amazon Web Services (AWS) Cloud Practitioner

July 2022

Amazon Inc.

Cisco Certified Network Professional (CCNP R & S)

Feb 2011 - Expired

Cisco Systems

Nigeria Society of Engineers (NSE)

2011 - present

NSE, Nigeria

British Computer Society (BCS)

2022 - present

BCS. UK

Nigeria Computer Society (NCS)

2018 - present

NCS, Nigeria

Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers (IEEE) No: 92735619

2014 - present

IEEE, USA

Institue of Engineering Technology (IET)

2022 - present

IET, UK

Service and Volunteering

YouTube Tech Tutorials

2014 - Present

Hands-on free IT tutorials

* I present hands-on video tutorials on various aspects of Information Technology, emphasizing cybersecurity, Linux Server Administration, Windows, Computer Networks, and Automation. – View YouTube Channel

University of Glasgow

May 2021 – May 2022

School of Computing Science Systems Section Seminars

* Scheduling and hosting weekly seminars for the Systems research group

IEEE Journal

February 2021 – Present

Journal reviewer

AFRINIC

Reviewing conference and journal articles for the IEEE

Policy Development Working Group Member

May 2018 – Present

* Developing and discussing several resource policy proposals that AFRINIC implements towards distributing IPv4, IPv6 and ASN resources in Africa.

National Youth Service Corps - NYSC

March 2010 - March 2011

- Mathematics Teacher, Oluponna School, Osun, Nigeria * Teaching secondary school students in various mathematical concepts and theories, including assessments
 - * Develop lesson plans and curriculum aligned with the educational standards

Last updated on July 13, 2024

Page 2 of 3

Awards, Honours and Scholarships

Postgraduate research scholarship:	January 2023
School of Computing Science, University of Glasgow, UK	
Open Access Publication grant:	February 2022
UKRI - University of Glasgow, UK	
IEEE Netsoft 2022 Conference grant:	July 2022
School of Computing Science, University of Glasgow	v
PhD full scholarship award:	January 2020
PTDF Overseas Scholarship Scheme for PhD at the University of Glasgow, UK	
MSc full scholarship award:	September 2014
TetFUND Foreign Scholarship Award for MSc at the University of Hertfordshire, UK	
Selected Publications NFV, Switching, UNIX, Virtualization, Containers	
Leveraging NFV Heterogeneity at the Network Edge	Jan 2024
$PhD\ Thesis,\ University\ of\ Glasgow\ \underline{View\ publication}$	$United\ Kingdom$
Latency-aware vNF Placement on Heterogeneous Hosts at the Network Edge	Dec 2023
$IEEE\ Global\ Communications\ Conference\ -\ \underline{View\ publication}$	Malaysia
Performance Evaluation of Virtual Network Functions	July 2022
$IEEE\ Network\ Softwarization\ Conference\ -\ \underline{View\ publication}$	Milan, Italy

Network Function Virtualization Frameworks: Review of Challenges

MDPI Future Internet Journal - View publication

Feb 2022

Basel, Switzerland